Up to now we've seen how to make slices and
到目前为止 我们已经知道怎么用索引
select elements of an NumPy array using indices.
对 NumPy 数组进行切片并选择其元素了
This is useful when we know the exact indices of the elements we want to select.
如果我们知道目标元素的具体索引 这些方法的确很实用
However, there are many situations in
但很多时候
which we don't know the indices of the elements we want.
我们并不清楚目标元素的索引
For example; Suppose we have a 10,000 by 10,000 array of random integers
比如 假设我们有一个 10000 x 10000 的随机整数数组
ranging from one to 15,000 and we only want to select integers that are less than 20.
其范围在 1 到 15000 之间 但我们只想选出其中小于 20 的整数
Boolean indexing can help us in these cases by helping us select
这个时候布尔索引就派上了用场
elements using logical arguments instead of explicit indices.
借助逻辑参数而非具体索引 布尔索引能帮我们选出想要的元素
Let's see some examples.
我们来看些例子
Consider this five by five array ranging from zero to 24.
这是个 5 x 5 的数组 范围在 0 到 24 之间
We can use boolean indexing to select elements greater than 10.
我们可以用布尔索引选出大于 10 的元素
Like this. Instead of indices,
像这样 这个时候我们不用索引
we are using a boolean expression.
而是用布尔表达式
Let's also get the elements that are less than or equal to seven.
我们还可以提取出小于或等于 7 的元素
And now both greater than seven and less than 17.
或者大于 7 且小于 17 的元素
We can use boolean indexing to assign the elements that are
我们还可以用布尔索引
between 10 and 17 to the value of negative one.
给 10 到 17 之间的元素赋值 使其值变为 -1
In addition to Boolean indexing,
除了布尔索引
NumPy also allows for set operations.
NumPy 还能进行集合运算
This is useful when comparing two NumPy arrays.
这很方便我们比较两个 NumPy 数组
For example, to find common elements.
比如找出数组的共同元素
Consider these two rank one arrays.
来看这两个秩为 1 的数组
We can create arrays for the intersection, difference, and union.
我们可以进行交、差、并集合运算 从而创建新数组
Like this. We can also sort NumPy arrays.
像这样 我们还可以给 NumPy 数组排序
Let's use NumPy sort function to sort rank one and rank two arrays in different ways.
我们来用 NumPy 函数 sort 分别给秩为 1 和秩为 2 的数组排序
Like with other functions we saw before,
和我们之前看到的其它函数一样
the sort function can also be used as a method.
函数 sort 也可以当方法用
However, there's a big difference on how the data is stored in memory in this case.
但其数据在内存中的存储方式会有所不同
When sort is used as a function,
如果把 sort 当函数用
it sorts the NumPy array out of place,
函数会在别的地方对 NumPy 数组进行排序
meaning they don't change the original array.
也就是说 操作不会改变原数组
However, when you use sort as a method,
如果将 sort 当方法用
the array is sorted in place,
那数组会在原地进行排序
meaning the original array is changed.
也即原数组也会有变化
Let's create an unsorted rank one array.
我们先创建一个秩为 1 的无序数组
We can sort x using sort as a function.
把 sort 当作函数 给 x 排序
This will sort x out of place and leave the original array as is.
函数会在其它地方给 x 排序 不改动原数组
As you can see Numpy.sort did sort the x array,
正如你所见 np.sort 的确对 x 数组进行了排序
but x itself did not change.
但 x 本身没有变化
Notice that this sorts the array and leaves repeating values.
注意 排序操作不会删除重复元素
If you want to sort only the unique elements in x,
如果不想排序后 x 还有重复元素
you can combine it with a unique function like this.
你可以结合使用 sort 和函数 unique 就像这样
Now, let's see how we can sort arrays in place by using sort as a method. Here's x again.
现在 我们来看怎么把 sort 当方法用 在原地给数组排序 还是这个数组 x
If we sort x like this,
像这样给数组排序
we will see that this affects the original x and sorts it.
我们会发现 原数组 x 也排好序了
When sorting rank two arrays,
在给秩为 2 的数组排序时
we need to tell the sort function whether we are sorting by rows or by columns.
我们得告诉函数 sort 排序应按行还是按列进行
This is done by using the keyword axis.
因此我们要用关键字 axis
Here is an unsorted rank two array.
这是个秩为 2 的无序数组
We can sort x by rows like this,
我们可以像这样按行对 x 进行排序 如图
which you can see here or we can sort X by columns like this, which you can see up here.
也可以像这样按列对 x 进行排序 如图